ذَرْنِي وَمَنْ خَلَقْتُ وَحِيدًا - 74:11
Leave Me with the one I created alone
وَجَعَلْتُ لَهُ مَالًا مَّمْدُودًا - 74:12
And to whom I granted extensive wealth
وَبَنِينَ شُهُودًا - 74:13 وَمَهَّدتُّ لَهُ تَمْهِيدًا - 74:14
And children present [with him]. And spread [everything] before him, easing [his life].
ثُمَّ يَطْمَعُ أَنْ أَزِيدَ - 74:15 كَلَّا ۖ إِنَّهُ كَانَ لِآيَاتِنَا عَنِيدًا - 74:16
Then he desires that I should add more. No! Indeed, he has been toward Our verses obstinate.
سَأُرْهِقُهُ صَعُودًا - 74:17 إِنَّهُ فَكَّرَ وَقَدَّرَ - 74:18 فَقُتِلَ كَيْفَ قَدَّرَ - 74:19
I will cover him with arduous torment. Indeed, he thought and deliberated. So may he be destroyed [for] how he deliberated.
ثُمَّ قُتِلَ كَيْفَ قَدَّرَ - 74:20 ثُمَّ نَظَرَ - 74:21 ثُمَّ عَبَسَ وَبَسَرَ - 74:22
Then may he be destroyed [for] how he deliberated. Then he considered [again]; Then he frowned and scowled;
ثُمَّ أَدْبَرَ وَاسْتَكْبَرَ - 74:23 فَقَالَ إِنْ هَٰذَا إِلَّا سِحْرٌ يُؤْثَرُ - 74:24
Then he turned back and was arrogant. And said, "This is not but magic imitated [from others].
إِنْ هَٰذَا إِلَّا قَوْلُ الْبَشَرِ - 74:25 سَأُصْلِيهِ سَقَرَ - 74:26 وَمَا أَدْرَاكَ مَا سَقَرُ - 74:27
This is not but the word of a human being." I will drive him into Saqar. And what can make you know what is Saqar?
لَا تُبْقِي وَلَا تَذَرُ - 74:28 لَوَّاحَةٌ لِّلْبَشَرِ - 74:29 عَلَيْهَا تِسْعَةَ عَشَرَ - 74:30
It lets nothing remain and leaves nothing [unburned], blackening the skins. Over it are nineteen [angels].
أعوذ بالله من الشيطان الرجيم
I seek refuge in Allah from the accursed Satan.
بِسْمِ اللَّهِ الرَّحْمَٰنِ الرَّحِيمِ
In the name of Allah, the Entirely Merciful, the Especially Merciful.
يَا أَيُّهَا الْمُدَّثِّرُ - 74:1 قُمْ فَأَنذِرْ - 74:2 وَرَبَّكَ فَكَبِّرْ - 74:3
O you who covers himself [with a garment], arise and warn and your Lord glorify.
وَثِيَابَكَ فَطَهِّرْ - 74:4 وَالرُّجْزَ فَاهْجُرْ - 74:5 وَلَا تَمْنُن تَسْتَكْثِرُ - 74:6
And your clothing purify. And uncleanliness avoid. And do not confer favor to acquire more.
وَلِرَبِّكَ فَاصْبِرْ - 74:7 فَإِذَا نُقِرَ فِي النَّاقُورِ - 74:8 فَذَٰلِكَ يَوْمَئِذٍ يَوْمٌ عَسِيرٌ - 74:9
But for your Lord be patient. And when the trumpet is blown, that Day will be a difficult day.
عَلَى الْكَافِرِينَ غَيْرُ يَسِيرٍ - 74:10
For the disbelievers - not easy.
ذَرْنِي وَمَنْ خَلَقْتُ وَحِيدًا - 74:11
Leave Me with the one I created alone
وَجَعَلْتُ لَهُ مَالًا مَّمْدُودًا - 74:12
And to whom I granted extensive wealth
وَبَنِينَ شُهُودًا - 74:13 وَمَهَّدتُّ لَهُ تَمْهِيدًا - 74:14
And children present [with him]. And spread [everything] before him, easing [his life].
ثُمَّ يَطْمَعُ أَنْ أَزِيدَ - 74:15 كَلَّا ۖ إِنَّهُ كَانَ لِآيَاتِنَا عَنِيدًا - 74:16
Then he desires that I should add more. No! Indeed, he has been toward Our verses obstinate.
سَأُرْهِقُهُ صَعُودًا - 74:17 إِنَّهُ فَكَّرَ وَقَدَّرَ - 74:18 فَقُتِلَ كَيْفَ قَدَّرَ - 74:19
I will cover him with arduous torment. Indeed, he thought and deliberated. So may he be destroyed [for] how he deliberated.
ثُمَّ قُتِلَ كَيْفَ قَدَّرَ - 74:20 ثُمَّ نَظَرَ - 74:21 ثُمَّ عَبَسَ وَبَسَرَ - 74:22
Then may he be destroyed [for] how he deliberated. Then he considered [again]; Then he frowned and scowled;
ثُمَّ أَدْبَرَ وَاسْتَكْبَرَ - 74:23 فَقَالَ إِنْ هَٰذَا إِلَّا سِحْرٌ يُؤْثَرُ - 74:24
Then he turned back and was arrogant. And said, "This is not but magic imitated [from others].
إِنْ هَٰذَا إِلَّا قَوْلُ الْبَشَرِ - 74:25 سَأُصْلِيهِ سَقَرَ - 74:26 وَمَا أَدْرَاكَ مَا سَقَرُ - 74:27
This is not but the word of a human being." I will drive him into Saqar. And what can make you know what is Saqar?
لَا تُبْقِي وَلَا تَذَرُ - 74:28 لَوَّاحَةٌ لِّلْبَشَرِ - 74:29 عَلَيْهَا تِسْعَةَ عَشَرَ - 74:30
It lets nothing remain and leaves nothing [unburned], blackening the skins. Over it are nineteen [angels].
وَمَا جَعَلْنَا أَصْحَابَ النَّارِ إِلَّا مَلَائِكَةً ۙ وَمَا جَعَلْنَا عِدَّتَهُمْ إِلَّا فِتْنَةً
And We have not made the keepers of the Fire except angels. And We have not made their number except as a trial
َمَا جَعَلْنَا عِدَّتَهُمْ إِلَّا فِتْنَةً لِّلَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا
And We have not made their number except as a trial for those who disbelieve
لِيَسْتَيْقِنَ الَّذِينَ أُوتُوا الْكِتَابَ
that those who were given the Scripture will be convinced
لِيَسْتَيْقِنَ الَّذِينَ أُوتُوا الْكِتَابَ وَيَزْدَادَ الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا إِيمَانًا ۙ
that those who were given the Scripture will be convinced and those who have believed will increase in faith
وَلَا يَرْتَابَ الَّذِينَ أُوتُوا الْكِتَابَ وَالْمُؤْمِنُونَ ۙ وَلِيَقُولَ الَّذِينَ فِي قُلُوبِهِم مَّرَضٌ
and those who were given the Scripture and the believers will not doubt and that those in whose hearts is hypocrisy
وَلِيَقُولَ الَّذِينَ فِي قُلُوبِهِم مَّرَضٌ وَالْكَافِرُونَ مَاذَا أَرَادَ اللَّهُ بِهَٰذَا مَثَلًا
and that those in whose hearts is hypocrisy and the disbelievers will say, "What does Allah intend by this as an example?"
كَذَٰلِكَ يُضِلُّ اللَّهُ مَن يَشَاءُ وَيَهْدِي مَن يَشَاءُ ۚ
Thus does Allah leave astray whom He wills and guides whom He wills.
وَمَا يَعْلَمُ جُنُودَ رَبِّكَ إِلَّا هُوَ ۚ وَمَا هِيَ إِلَّا ذِكْرَىٰ لِلْبَشَرِ - 74:31
And none knows the soldiers of your Lord except Him. And mention of the Fire is not but a reminder to humanity.
كَلَّا وَالْقَمَرِ - 74:32 وَاللَّيْلِ إِذْ أَدْبَرَ - 74:33 وَالصُّبْحِ إِذَا أَسْفَرَ - 74:34
No! By the moon. And [by] the night when it departs. And [by] the morning when it brightens,
إِنَّهَا لَإِحْدَى الْكُبَرِ - 74:35 نَذِيرًا لِّلْبَشَرِ - 74:36 لِمَن شَاءَ مِنكُمْ أَن يَتَقَدَّمَ أَوْ يَتَأَخَّرَ - 74:37
Indeed, the Fire is of the greatest [afflictions]. As a warning to humanity- to whoever wills among you to proceed or stay behind.
كُلُّ نَفْسٍ بِمَا كَسَبَتْ رَهِينَةٌ - 74:38
Every soul, for what it has earned, will be retained
إِلَّا أَصْحَابَ الْيَمِينِ - 74:39 فِي جَنَّاتٍ يَتَسَاءَلُونَ - 74:40
Except the companions of the right, [Who will be] in gardens, questioning each other
عَنِ الْمُجْرِمِينَ - 74:41 مَا سَلَكَكُمْ فِي سَقَرَ - 74:42 قَالُوا لَمْ نَكُ مِنَ الْمُصَلِّينَ - 74:43
About the criminals, [And asking them], "What put you into Saqar?" They will say, "We were not of those who prayed,
وَلَمْ نَكُ نُطْعِمُ الْمِسْكِينَ - 74:44 وَكُنَّا نَخُوضُ مَعَ الْخَائِضِينَ - 74:45
Nor did we used to feed the poor. And we used to enter into vain discourse with those who engaged [in it],
وَكُنَّا نُكَذِّبُ بِيَوْمِ الدِّينِ-74:46 حَتَّىٰ أَتَانَا الْيَقِينُ -74:47
And we used to deny the Day of Recompense until there came to us the certainty."
فَمَا تَنفَعُهُمْ شَفَاعَةُ الشَّافِعِينَ - 74:48
So there will not benefit them the intercession of [any] intercessors.
فَمَا لَهُمْ عَنِ التَّذْكِرَةِ مُعْرِضِينَ - 74:49 كَأَنَّهُمْ حُمُرٌ مُّسْتَنفِرَةٌ - 74:50
Then what is [the matter] with them that they are, from the reminder, turning away. As if they were alarmed donkeys-
فَرَّتْ مِن قَسْوَرَةٍ - 74:51
Fleeing from a lion?
بَلْ يُرِيدُ كُلُّ امْرِئٍ مِّنْهُمْ أَن يُؤْتَىٰ صُحُفًا مُّنَشَّرَةً - 74:52
Rather, every person among them desires that he would be given scriptures spread about.
كَلَّا ۖ بَل لَّا يَخَافُونَ الْآخِرَةَ - 74:53 كَلَّا إِنَّهُ تَذْكِرَةٌ - 74:54
No! But they do not fear the Hereafter. No! Indeed, the Qur'an is a reminder.
فَمَن شَاءَ ذَكَرَهُ - 74:55
Then whoever wills will remember it.
وَمَا يَذْكُرُونَ إِلَّا أَن يَشَاءَ اللَّهُ ۚ هُوَ أَهْلُ التَّقْوَىٰ وَأَهْلُ الْمَغْفِرَةِ - 74:56
And they will not remember except that Allah wills. He is worthy of fear and adequate for [granting] forgiveness.